<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: posts in english | Mirko Caserta]]></title>
  <link href="http://mcaserta.github.com/blog/categories/posts-in-english/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mcaserta.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-19T20:31:16+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://mcaserta.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mirko Caserta]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clustering Issues?]]></title>
    <link href="http://mcaserta.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/clustering-issues/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-24T14:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mcaserta.github.com/blog/2012/09/24/clustering-issues</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The number one culprit for a non working cluster is a misconfigured /etc/hosts file. This is because of how some software implementation announces its availability on the network. Typically, if you have a resolver configured so that the domain name of your local node points to the loopback address, you have a problem.</p>

<p>Some Linux distributions (Ubuntu, I’m looking at you!) ship with an /etc/hosts that looks like this (supposing the hostname is cat and the domain name is foo.bar):</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><figcaption><span>/etc/hosts </span></figcaption>
<div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>127.0.0.1    localhost
</span><span class='line'>127.0.1.1    cat.foo.bar cat</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>For some reason, a few software implementations use the resolver to infer the address of the node they’re running on, then start sending out messages such as “Hey, I’m available. You can find me at 127.0.1.1”, which is the problem because you want the node to advertise its availability with a real ip address (usually the one that is bound to the main network interface).</p>

<p>The solution is to get rid of the 127.0.1.1 line. You’re welcome.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spring Crypto Utils 1.3.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://mcaserta.github.com/blog/2012/08/27/spring-crypto-utils-1.3.0/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-27T14:47:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://mcaserta.github.com/blog/2012/08/27/spring-crypto-utils-1.3.0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve released a new version of Spring Crypto Utils. The project now has a gorgeous, shiny, sleek, new website on the <a href="http://springcryptoutils.com" title="Spring Crypto Utils">springcryptoutils.com</a> domain. The website is made possible thanks to the kind folks at <a href="https://github.com/" title="GitHub">GitHub</a> and their <a href="http://pages.github.com/" title="GitHub Pages">GitHub pages</a> hosting facility.</p>

<p>Please read the notes in the <a href="http://springcryptoutils.com/changelog.html" title="Spring Crypto Utils: ChangeLog">changelog</a> if you’re upgrading.</p>

<p>I must say moving to GitHub was a smart move since contributing to the project is very much easier now thanks to git pull requests. I would like to thank Chad Johnston and Martin Bosak for their contributions: respectively, <a href="https://github.com/mcaserta/spring-crypto-utils/commit/b0c7e8dab8c3f9ead869055aa460feb0dc5af4f6">the certificate element</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/mcaserta/spring-crypto-utils/commit/15f305e522bd3c85eec7cc46a50e18385f324b9e">provider attribute</a>.</p>

<p>I hope users will find the documentation easier to read. Here is an example regarding <a href="http://springcryptoutils.com/signature-m.html">digital signatures with runtime selection of multiple keys</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
